today I have for you a Super Fresh
straight out of the oven new web API
that is incredibly cool when we use
mobile applications either iOS or
Android and we move between screens we
are used to seeing animations happen
maybe one element is animated maybe the
new screen fades in maybe it shows from
the bottom or slides from the side
creating animations like this for our
website is not impossible but it is no
work in the park either you would have
to maybe detect when the user clicks on
the link and then you will have to
render and start animating the next page
while still showing the old page and
when the animation finishes then you
will remove the old page not impossible
but it sounds like a lot of work enter
the view transitions API with the view
transitions API we can add beautiful
transitions between pages to our website
by only using HTML code let me show you
here we have two simple HTML pages on
the index page we have a link to the doc
HTML page and on the dog HTML page there
is an image and a title with the code as
it is when I click on the link there
will be no transition to get the
transition all we have to do is add a
meta tag with the name view transition
to the head of both of our pages and now
when we click on the link we will
automatically get a fade in transition
when we navigate that is already super
cool but if we want to we can customize
the animations between Pages using CSS
before we do that we have to understand
how this API works when the API is
enabled and we click on a link the
browser will take a screenshot of the
old page it will capture a live
representation of the new page and
animate the change between them on our
CSS we get access to both of these
elements the old screenshot and the new
page if you want to customize the
animation when the old page is
disappearing you can use the view
transition old pseudo elements and if
you want to customize the animation when
the new page appears you can use the
view transition new sudo element in our
case we're going to add this code
selecting those pseudo elements to both
of our Pages which as you can see makes
the animation slower when we change
between pages but that is not all we can
create our own animations like for
example making the old page slide to the
left and making the new page slide from
the right for this on the old page we
are going to create an animation that is
going to change the opacity of the page
to zero and move it to the left and
we're going to give that animation to
the view transition old sudo element and
then on the new page we will make an
animation that initializes the page with
zero opacity and moves it to the right
and we are going to give that animation
to the view transition new sudo element
and as you can see when we click on the
link we have a very nice animation that
makes our web look look like a native
app that is already super cool but what
if I told you that we can also animate
elements between screens for this on our
index page we are going to put a small
photo of a dog with a link to the dock
page and on the Doc Page we will show
the same photo just a little bigger plus
some extra text again here only because
we are using that magical meta tag we
get the nice fade animation but now
we're going to use CSS to tell the
browser that we want to animate the
image between the two screens the way we
do this is by using the view transition
name CSS property to tell the browser
that this image is the same across the
screen that is why we are naming the
image dog in both our index HTML and
doc.html and as you can see just with
that line of code now the browser will
animate the image when the page changes
how cool was that the view transitions
API also works with JavaScript so you
can use it from react or other framework
all you have to do is call document that
start view transition and run whatever
code your framework uses to navigate and
you're good to go now it's time for some
bad news this API is still experimental
and as of some days ago the only browser
that supports it fully is Google Chrome
version 111 in Chrome for Android which
means that we have to wait for all the
other browsers to adopt it Microsoft
Edge and Opera are on the way it seems
like Firefox will support it as well and
we would have to wait and see if Safari
eventually does that's it for this video
I hope that you found it useful and
don't forget that if you want to learn
things like JavaScript python react
react native gold Dart flutter among
many others for absolutely free all you
have to do is click the link below to
join any of our many free courses that
you can take right now for free with me
click on the link below and I will see
you there
mobile see you on the next one bye
thank you